Fork is an XPGE 4.2 function which creates a duplicate process referred to as a child
process.
The process that issues the fork is referred to as the parent process.
A parent process can create multiple child processes.
With ZOS Unix, a program that issues a fork creates a new address base which is a copy
of the address base where the program is running.
The fork function does a program call to the kernel which uses Workload Manager to
create the child process.
The contents of the parent address space are then copied to the child address space.
After the fork function, the code in the child address space is at the same address as the
parent address space.
Control is returned to both programs at the same point.
The only difference that the application sees is the return code from the fork function.
A return code of 0 is returned to the child after a successful fork, or other return codes
are valid only for the parent.
A process can also be created when a non-ZOS Unix program requests a ZOS Unix service.
For example, an open of a file in the hierarchical file system from an assembler program.
This address space is dubbed as a ZOS Unix process.
The dub does not result in the new address space being created.
The child address space is almost an identical copy of the parent address space.
User data, for example, private subpools and system data like RTM or Recovery Termination
Management Control blocks are identical.
HFS files are allocated to the kernel and IO is done by coding the kernel.
On a fork, all open files are inherited by the child address space.
ZOS data sets are allocated to an individual address space.
After a fork, the child address space does not have access to the ZOS data sets allocated
by the parent.
Through system definitions, there is a way to improve the performance of fork calls.
The option allows the parent and child processes to share a copy of the storage areas until
they're modified.
When the area is modified, it's copied to the child process.
If this option is off, the system creates a copy of all storage areas at the time of
the fork for the child process.
The XPG 4.2 standard defines a family of exec function calls.
The exec functions are used to start execution of a new program.
The difference between the exec functions is the way the name of the program and the parameters
of the arguments are passed.
When a program issues an exec system call, the program, as well as all the data in the
address space, is destroyed.
The new program is loaded from the file system and given control.
The only information the new program has access to is the arguments passed on the exec
call.
The fork and exec functions are usually used together in a sequence.
First a process issues the fork to create a child process.
The result is two almost identical processes which run the same program, let's say Program
A.
An important difference between the processes is the return code from the fork.
Only the child process receives a return code of zero after a successful fork.
This can be used as a way of starting a new program.
Program A issues an exec to start a new program, Program C, if the return code is zero.
In this case the child has a zero return code and Program C is indeed started.
The parent gets a return code different from zero from the fork and it continues to run
Program A.
The result of all this is that the parent process runs the old program, Program A, while
the child process runs the new program, Program C.
The two processes are related and they can share data and information between them.
In order to enable multiprocess applications to run on ZOS Unix without the address space
resource overhead, ZOS Unix provides services that allow multiple processes within one address
space.
These types of processes are called local processes.
The child process is called a local child process.
The local child process has the same attributes as a child process after a fork and exec.
There is a setDubDefaultService which provides the ability for a ZOS task to attach a new
sub-task that runs as a new process.
This new process is called a non-forked local process.
The spawn function implements local processes.
It also combines the fork and the exec into a single call.
It extends the support for local processes to the standard family of C services.
If the environment variable underscore bpx underscore share as is set to yes, the parent
and child processes created by a spawn share the same address space.
If that environment variable is set to no, each process runs in its own address space
as in a fork.
In the next video, we'll talk about a communication for sending data between processes.